hey folks this is Chris lofflin
I'm here doing music series
and today
we're going to talk about some contemporary RMV
and neo soul bass playing
so get your base and let's play some soul music
hey folk so that was kind of an example of
a track that you might hear and is considered to be
contemporary R m B
or even neo soul
the term neo soul is actually more of an
industry term that it actually is a musical one
it's it kind of categorizes the music of
mid 90s early 2 thousands
artists like the Angelo and America badu and Maxwell
and
those kinds of folks
when they 1st got started their sound was
a lot different than
some of the other music that was popular at the time
and they went back to
really soulful singing they went back to
really warm sounds and things
and it reminded everybody of
the music that happened in the 70s and the 60s and
uh that's kind of how they wanted to call it
neo soul new soul
but it had all the same traditions as those
but it added some influences too
it added uh electronic music
it added hip hop was a huge influence
uh reggae African music Latin musics
um even lots of different forms of rock music
so it was just a culmination of
of all of the music that
those people grew up listening to
and they just made really warm
soulful sounding music out of it
um
there's definitely a a
a way to approach playing this music
uh the drums are
probably the biggest influence
that you'll have in this music
unlike say some forms of rock or even some
forms of funk music where um
the baseline is really prevalent
the drums are kind of what
everything is based on
so we listen to those and we play along with those
following those a lot of times
and there's a couple different ways of approaching
making baselines for this stuff
or even playing the baselines that are on the records
so what I like to do is
kind of put on a track and us listen to
maybe some things that we could listen for and
and actually some scales and things that we can use
all of that good stuff
so let's get started
so the 1st thing I want us to do is listen to the drums
and one thing that I like to do to get started is
listen to the kick drum especially
and follow that
now we have 2 choices
we can
play the rhythms that they're playing
and play long notes
or play short notes
okay
so the demonstration of playing long notes
let the note ring out
or we can play them short
both is a different feeling
we play it like this is
actually sounds more like the kick drum
or we can mix the 2
right now what you want to make sure that you have
is you have a really nice tone
now I'm playing it with my thumbs
it's actually called a thumb you
and what I'm doing is is with my right hand I'm just
instead of
see how that's a little bit more bright
has a little bit more of an edge
it's a little bit warmer
a little bit more dull
you want to actually
think like a drummer when you're playing this
now I'm playing over a C
once again one note baseline
and it's great
what I'm gonna do here is kind of um
introduce maybe some
some different notes or
different scales that we can use
now
the track itself has a keyboard part
and the course that
it'll play is actually is going to be 2 different
C chords it's gonna play a C minor chord
and it's gonna play a C major chord
so what we can do with both of those
is we can play in that box that we were talking about
so if I play in this box I'm playing
the root again I'm playing the 5th
and I'm also playing the octave
and I can use those notes
now they'll work over both chords
so what I like to do down is um
for that
last demonstration I just use one note
what we're gonna do now is
I'm gonna do some other notes
maybe some different scales that we can use
over the chords that will be playing over
so the 1st thing I wanna do is
reintroduce the box
us playing the root the 5th and the octave
so that's the root
that's the 5th
and that's the octave
that'll completely work over
both of the chords that we're going to play
but now what we're going to do is we're going to get
specific about
the scales that we use
1st one we're going to use is when I spoke about before
and that'll be a major pentatonic
so that shape is like this
all right so it'll be 24 one 4 one 4
now that's the major
we're going to do now is add a minor
so to play the minor
we're going to play
one
4 one 3 one
so once again it looks like a box
now those are going to be
specific to the chords that we're going to play to
alright so what I'm going to do now
is I'm going to put the track on
so we can hear the keyboard part
and then we're going to
play some base parts
that add those notes from those games
alright so now we hear keyboard part that 1st chord
is a C minor chord
this next chord
is a C major so we can use that box
over both
we can play them long
so now what we can do is we can use the specific scales
for the specific chords
and once again
we'll name the chords
right here is the minor
C minor it's a C major
C minor
see major
see minor
just
alternating between the 2
could be that simple right
those we played a little short
the snake example let's play them a little long
right so
hold on to him
I'm just
I'm just choosing random notes
but the rhythms of
what makes it sound good it makes it feel good
alright so
just keep practicing those
have fun with it
alternate between long and a short
now I'm playing with my thumb all over time
but you can play with your fingers too
sometimes
I just have a great time
and I'll see you in the next lesson